<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Hacking Fingerprint GUI</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Wolfgang</firstname>

      <surname>Ullrich</surname>

      <surname></surname>
    </author>

    <date>2015-06-29</date>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>For developers who want to understand and possible change something in
  the Fingerprint GUI project it might be required to give some hints about
  how the system works. It is assumed the reader of this document has a
  certain understanding of PAM.</para>

  <para>There are 6 executables and one library used:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>“<command>fingerprint-gui</command>”</para>

      <para>The main application to be used for discovering fingerprint
      scanners on the USB bus, acquiring (enrollment) and verification of
      fingerprints and testing the PAM settings.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>“<command>fingerprint-identifier</command>”</para>

      <para>An application for testing the identification of users by their
      fingerprints and to be used in special cases for any user-defined
      scripts in which a fingerprint identification is required.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>“<command>fingerprint-helper</command>”</para>

      <para>A helper application to be called out of PAM for requesting
      fingerprints while identifying or authenticating a user. This
      application should not be called from the command line.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>“<command>fingerprint-rw</command>”</para>

      <para>Another helper application to be called from “fingerprint-gui”
      and other modules when user settings and fingerprint (bir)
      data in
      “/var/lib/fingerprint-gui/” must be written or read.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>“<command>fingerprint-plugin</command>”</para>

      <para>A helper application to be plugged in into some other applications
      (like gnome-screensaver) that don't allow other GUI applications to be
      displayed on top of their own screen. This application should not be
      called from the command line.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>“<command>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</command>”</para>

      <para>A PAM module that is called by PAM when a user has to be
      identified or authenticated by their fingerprint.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>“<command>fingerprint-polkit-agent</command>”</para>

      <para>An authentication agent for policykit-1 with fingerprint
      recognition.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <sect1>
    <title>Debug Output</title>

    <para>All modules accept a “<parameter>debug</parameter>” (or
    “<parameter>-d</parameter>” or “<parameter>--debug</parameter>”) argument
    to be given for execution. This argument causes a lot of debug output
    printed to syslog. Depending on syslog settings the output might be
    printed to “<filename>/var/log/auth.log</filename>”,
    “<filename>/var/log/messages</filename>” or
    “<filename>/var/log/syslog</filename>”.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>fingerprint-gui</title>

    <para>This software should be self explanatory. So no further information
    is needed at the moment. When running, a users manual is available in the
    help menu.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>fingerprint-identifier</title>

    <para>This program first tries to collect all stored fingerprint data of
    all users from user-specific directories in
    “<filename>/var/lib/fingerprint-gui/&lt;username&gt;/&lt;drivername&gt;/</filename>”.
    If a directory named after the user is available and can be read it
    collects all fingerprint data and tries to identify the user after a
    finger swipe was given. If it doesn't run with root permissions the
    directories of other users are not readable. In this case the fingerprints
    of the current user are accessible only. So only the current user can be
    identified or authenticated. After a successful authentication the user's
    login name is printed to stdout and the program exits.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>fingerprint-helper</title>

    <para>All Fingerprint GUI modules are developed using the Qt system,
    except the
    “<application><filename>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</filename></application>”
    module. This means the executables create a QApplication or a
    QCoreApplication object when running. Qt doesn't allow more than one of
    these objects to be created in an executable. Now, if some other Qt
    application would call PAM for authenticating a user and PAM would call
    the “<application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application>” library this would
    cause a crash, when “<application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application>”
    would try to create a (second) QApplication or QCoreApplication object
    while prompting for a finger swipe. Therefore
    <application>“<filename>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</filename>”</application>
    is not a Qt application but forks a child process (the
    <application><filename>fingerprint-helper</filename></application>) to
    prompt the user for a finger swipe and handle fingerprints.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>fingerprint-rw</title>

    <para>
    This application
    is called via two symlinks (<application>fingerprint-rw-read</application> and <application>fingerprint-rw-write</application>)
    and should not be called from the command
    line. Since version 1.07 files and directories in “<filename>/var/lib/fingerprint-gui/</filename>” are owned by
    root.root. Subdirectories have mode 655. Files have mode 600. For security reasons 
    "fingerprint-rw" requests additional user authentication via polkit when creating 
    subdirectories and writing files.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>fingerprint-plugin</title>

    <para>Some applications (namely
    "<application>gnome-screensaver</application>") don't accept for security
    reasons any GUI window to be displayed on top of their own screen. This
    means if <application>gnome-screensaver</application> calls PAM to prompt
    the user for authentication for the screensaver to be unlocked, the
    “<application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application>” module is called by
    PAM. This module forkes the
    “<application>fingerprint-helper</application>” process to request a
    finger swipe, but the window of this process is not visible (it is
    displayed “under” the locked screen). Therefore an additional
    “<application>fingerprint-plugin</application>” was created. This
    application is “plugged in” into the
    <application>gnome-screensaver</application> the same way an “embedded
    keyboard command” would be (by
    <application>gnome-screensaver</application> configuration).</para>

    <para>When <application>gnome-screensaver</application> starts its unlock
    prompt, it starts the “<application>fingerprint-plugin</application>”
    module. This module plugs into the screensaver and is displayed below the
    normal unlock prompt. Then the
    “<application>fingerprint-plugin</application>” listens for “display
    commands” at a named pipe “<filename>/tmp/fingerprint-plugin</filename>”.
    The “<application>fingerprint-helper</application>” process, forked from
    “<application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application>” finds this named pipe
    and sends all strings to be displayed at the GUI to this pipe. If no
    fingerprints for the user are available a “stop” command is sent to the
    pipe that causes the “<application>fingerprint-plugin</application>” to
    exit before “fingerprint-helper” exits itself. If some other command has
    to be displayed to the user (e.g. “ready...” or “authenticating
    &lt;username&gt;”) this command will be received by
    “<application>fingerprint-plugin</application>” via it's named pipe and
    then displayed on its GUI window.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</title>

    <para>This is the PAM module to be called out of PAM in case some
    application requests authentication. When its
    “<function>pam_sm_authenticate</function>” entry is called the module
    determines whether DISPLAY and XAUTHORITY environment variables are
    available. If DISPLAY is available and <anchor id="DDE_LINK" />XAUTHORITY
    is missing the module tries to find the xauthority filename by searching
    the command line of the X display process. If it was found
    “<application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application>” sets the  XAUTHORITY
    environment variable.</para>

    <para>The module then creates an anonymous pipe and forkes into a child
    process. This process executes
    “<application>fingerprint-helper</application>” with pipe, display, PAM
    service to authenticate and username (if available) as arguments. After
    forking, a random number (10 digits) is sent to the child process via the
    anonymous pipe. This number will be given back (via the anonymous pipe) as
    a “password” if the user was identified or authenticated by his
    fingerprint. If the helper process has sent something to the pipe, it uses
    libfakekey or uinput to exit the “PAM conversation function”.</para>

    <para>The parent process then calls the “PAM conversation function” of the
    calling application for prompting the username and/or password by keyboard
    while the child process (<application>fingerprint-helper</application>)
    prompts the user for swiping their finger.</para>

    <para>Now the two processes wait for input in the following cases:</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Case 1 (username was given by keyboard)</title>

      <para><anchor id="DDE_LINK5" />The PAM conversation function returns to
      the parent process (<application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application>)
      with a non empty username. This means the user did type his name on the
      keyboard. The helper process is stopped immediately by sending SIGUSR1
      to it, the helper widget disappears and the user must type his password
      for login.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Case 2 (user was identified by fingerprint)</title>

      <para>In this case the child process
      (<application>fingerprint-helper</application>) writes &lt;enter&gt; to
      the prompt using libfakekey or uinput and sends the username of the
      identified user via the pipe to his parent process
      (<application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application>). So the PAM
      conversation function returns an empty username field.
      <application>Pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application> then polls the fifo
      for a username and, if it can read it, sets this username to the PAM
      stack and sends SIGUSR1 to the helper. The helper then continues with
      case 3 below.</para>

      <para>If there is nothing in the pipe to read, the user might have typed
      &lt;enter&gt; on the keyboard. In this case
      <application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application> sends SIGUSR2 to the
      helper to stop it immediately and returns PAM_AUTHINFO_UNAVAIL.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Case 3 (user was known already; authentication)</title>

      <para>If the helper process has given the username to
      <application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application> via the pipe and
      receives SIGUSR1 it tries to get the users password from an encrypted
      file on the external media (USB stick, see 9. below). If available it
      sends this password via the pipe to
      <application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application>. If no “real” password
      is available it sends the random number to the pipe. Then the helper
      sends the &lt;enter&gt; key to the PAM prompt (via libfakekey or uinput)
      and exits. The same procedure happens, when the helper was forked with a
      known username from
      <application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application>.</para>

      <para>Then the PAM module returns from its password prompt with an empty
      password. It polls the pipe for the password and compares this with the
      random number. If it matches, there was no “real” password available and
      the module returns PAM_SUCCESS. If it doesn't match it is the “real”
      password of this user. The PAM module then sets this password to the PAM
      stack and returns PAM_IGNORE. This causes the other PAM modules in the
      PAM stack to check the given username against this password.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Case 4 (user has typed the password)</title>

      <para>If the PAM module returns from its password prompt with a non
      empty password field the user has typed his password at the prompt. Then
      the module sends SIGUSR2 to the helper to stop it immediately and
      returns PAM_IGNORE. So the other PAM modules can check the given
      username/password.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Using the “try_first_identified” argument</title>

    <para>The <application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application> module allows
    to be called with the argument
    “<parameter>try_first_identified</parameter>”. This allows calling the
    module more then once in a given PAM stack without the effect to request a
    finger swipe more then once. If the user was successful
    identified/authenticated by his fingerprint in the first call of
    <application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application> the module saves this
    username to the PAM stack by a “pam_set_data” call. If
    <application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application> is then called a second
    time with the “<parameter>try_first_identified</parameter>” argument, it
    tries to read this username by a “<function>pam_get_data</function>” call.
    If there is a username available and this name matches the current
    username to be authenticated, it returns PAM_SUCCESS immediately.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Saving Passwords to Removable Media</title>

    <para>With “<application>fingerprint-gui</application>” (“Password” Tab)
    the user can chose some directory on a mounted removable media, invoke his
    login password and save it to this media. This way the system can provide
    the login password to PAM while the user logs in with fingerprint to avoid
    a password request when e.g. gnome-keyring has to be opened or an
    encrypted home directory has to be mounted.</para>

    <para>This login password information is split into 2 different
    locations:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A file
        “<filename>&lt;username&gt;@&lt;machinename&gt;.xml</filename>” in a
        subdirectory “<filename>.fingerprints</filename>” on the chosen
        removable media, containing the encrypted password;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A file “<filename>config.xml</filename>” in the directory
        “<filename>/var/lib/fingerprint-gui/&lt;username&gt;</filename>”
        containing the path to the
        “<filename>&lt;username&gt;@&lt;machinename&gt;.xml</filename>” file,
        the UUID of the chosen partition on removable media and the key for
        decrypting the password.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The password is encrypted with a random symmetric key
    (AES128-CBC-PKS7).</para>

    <para><remark>THERE IS A SECURITY RISK</remark> when this user is not the
    only one who has root access to the machine! Someone with root permission
    could connect to this machine (e.g. via <application>ssh</application>)
    and copy the “<filename>config.xml</filename>” file and the
    “<filename>&lt;username&gt;@&lt;machinename&gt;.xml</filename>” from the
    connected removable media and then decrypt the user's password.</para>

    <para>When configured (see users manual) and the removable media is
    connected while fingerprint login, the system takes the following
    steps:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>After the user is identified (by fingerprint) the
        “<application>fingerprint-helper</application>” looks for the user's
        “<filename>/var/lib/fingerprint-gui/&lt;username&gt;/config.xml</filename>”
         and, if found, reads the UUID, the decryption key and the
        initialization vector;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Then creates a temporary directory
        “<filename>/tmp/&lt;UUID&gt;</filename>” and tries to mount the
        partition with this UUID there;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Then reads the encrypted key from
        “<filename>&lt;username&gt;@&lt;machinename&gt;.xml</filename>” file
        and unmounts the media immediately;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If the password can be decrypted it is given to
        <application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application> by an anonymous
        pipe;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <application>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</application> sets this
        password to PAM by a “<function>pam_set_item()</function>” call. If
        this call was successful it returns PAM_IGNORE. Then PAM calls the
        next module in stack (<application>pam_unix.so</application>) to
        validate username and password and complete the login process.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><remark>I'M NOT A CRYPTO EXPERT! If you are, please have a look at
    the sources (UserSettings.cpp) and let me know if there are possible
    problems.</remark></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Compiling the Sources</title>

    <para>You need the Qt4 environment (incl. libqca2) and the “developer”
    packages of the used libraries installed on your system for being able to
    compile the sources. You can then use the “<command>qmake-qt4</command>”
    command to create the makefiles for your system. Then call
    “<command>make</command>” and it will create all executables in
    “<filename>./bin/...</filename>” subdirectories. After binaries are
    successful created you can use “<command>sudo make install</command>” to
    copy them to their proper locations. If you have a fingerprint scanner
    manufactured by UPEK inc. or SGS Thomson, you can install the bundled
    proprietary driver “<application>libbsapi.so</application>” by executing
    “<command>sudo make install-upek</command>”. This is needed because the
    open source driver (in libfprint) lacks the ability of comparing
    one-to-many fingerprints. Please have a look into the README file for more
    informations about the build options.</para>

    <para>
    If you have fingerprint data created by a version 1.06 or below they have
    invalid ownership and permissions for version 1.07 or above. In this case you can 
    execute “<command>sudo make user-data</command>” to setup correct ownership and permissions
    of the existing files and directories for version 1.07.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>
