<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="">
  <title>Fingerprint GUI User's Manual</title>

  <subtitle>(Version 1.07)</subtitle>

  <articleinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Wolfgang</firstname>

      <surname>Ullrich</surname>
    </author>

    <date>2015/06/29</date>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>Fingerprint GUI is a set of tools for the use of fingerprint
    scanners on Linux systems. It enables recording and checking of
    fingerprint data and allows login and authentication of users by their
    fingerprint using a fingerprint scanner.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Security Advice</title>

      <para>The safety and reliability of the fingerprint-recognition depends
      very much on the hardware used, the associated device drivers and the
      software used to verify the biometric data. According to the current
      state of the art fingerprint recognition for security-critical
      applications is only limited suitable. More information about the safety
      of fingerprints can be found here: <ulink
      url="http://www.bromba.com/faq/fpfaqe.htm">http://www.bromba.com/faq/fpfaqe.htm</ulink></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>License</title>

      <para>Fingerprint GUI is subject to the GNU General Public License
      Version 2 (GPLv2) <ulink
      url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.html">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.html</ulink></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Fingerprint Enrollment</title>

    <para>Start the program "<command>Fingerprint GUI</command>" from the menu
    "<command>System | Preferences</command>”, or by the command:</para>

    <para>&gt; <command>fingerprint-gui -d</command></para>

    <para>in a terminal window. The argument "<parameter>-d</parameter>"
    generates debugging information to syslog (auth facility). You can find
    the log output in <filename>/var/log/auth.log</filename>.</para>

    <graphic fileref="start.png" />

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Choosing a Fingerprint Scanner</title>

      <para>In the “Devices” tab a list of all detected USB devices appears in
      the list “Attached USB Devices”. In the combo box “Finger Print Devices”
      appears a selection of the detected fingerprint scanners. If more than
      one fingerprint scanners have been detected, the desired scanner can be
      selected here. With the "Rescan" button, a re-examination on the USB bus
      can be initiated. By selecting "Show Vendor/Device" and "Show Driver
      Name" you can switch between displaying the device name or the device
      driver name.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Choosing a Finger</title>

      <para>With the "Next" button or by selecting the "Finger" tab you get
      the finger selection.</para>

      <graphic fileref="fingerchoice.png" />

      <para>Above the fingers are radio buttons. Here are the fingers marked
      green that are already enrolled. Select the finger to be
      detected.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Scanning and Verifying</title>

      <para>With the "Next" button or by selecting the tab "Scan/Verify" you
      get the card for enrolling or verifying of the fingerprint.</para>

      <graphic fileref="acquire.png" />

      <para>Now enroll the fingerprint. Depending on the scanner hardware, the
      driver software and the quality of the data you have to repeat this
      process until a message about the successful storage of the data
      appears.</para>

      <graphic fileref="saved.png" />

      <para>Click “Yes” to return to the finger choice if you want to enroll
      another finger or click “No” if you don't want it.</para>

      <para>If a finger was selected that has been enrolled already a dialog
      appears where this finger can be verified or newly enrolled.</para>

      <graphic fileref="verify.png" />

      <para>With the “Verify” button you can verify the existing fingerprint
      data against this finger. With “Acquire new” the existing fingerprint
      data for this finger is removed and the finger is newly enrolled. Click
      “Cancel” to go back to the finger choice.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Testing Settings and exporting Fingerprint Data</title>

    <para>With the "Next" button or by selecting the tab "Settings" you get
    the card for saving your fingerprint data and testing your PAM
    settings.</para>

    <graphic fileref="settings.png" />

    <para>By clicking “Export now” all existing fingerprint data of the
    current user are saved to a file. This is only required if these data need
    to be external backed up or if you want to use them on another computer. A
    file “<filename>Fingerprints.tar.gz</filename>“ will be created in the
    selected directory.</para>

    <para>With the “Test” button you can check the PAM settings for
    authentication. Chose the PAM service to be tested first then click
    “Test”. If all PAM settings for this service are correct the
    fingerprint-authentication dialog appears.</para>

    <graphic fileref="test.png" />

    <para>If a valid fingerprint was recognized a message “Authentication
    successful” appears in the text field.</para>

    <graphic fileref="success.png" />

    <para>If the fingerprint dialog doesn't appear some settings are invalid.
    You can stop the test by pressing the “Enter” key. A message “Fingerprint
    authentication failed” appears in the text field then.</para>

    <para><graphic depth="11.643cm" fileref="failed.png"
    width="14.553cm" /></para>

    <para>In this case the settings in the appropriate
    “<filename>/etc/pam.d/...</filename>“ file for this service are invalid
    and need to be corrected.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Saving a Password</title>

    <para>With the “Next” button or by selecting the “Password” tab you arrive
    at the dialog for storing a password to an external media.</para>

    <para><remark>PLEASE USE THIS FEATURE ONLY IF YOU COMPLETELY UNDERSTAND
    HOW IT WORKS. THIS FEATURE CAN OPEN A SECURITY RISK FOR YOUR
    DATA!</remark></para>

    <para><graphic depth="11.643cm" fileref="password.png"
    width="14.553cm" /></para>

    <para><remark>Explanation:</remark> If you use fingerprints for log-on to
    your system, no password is entered, since you were detected on the basis
    of your fingerprint. Depending on the configuration of your system a
    password might be needed to decrypt important data. For example this is
    the case if your home directory or the gnome-keyring is encrypted with
    your login password. Fingerprint GUI features the use of an external
    storage (USB stick) to store your password in an encrypted file on that
    media. If this media is connected to your computer while login, this file
    can be decrypted and the password can be used to unlock gnome-keyring or
    your home directory.</para>

    <para><remark>Security warning:</remark> Everyone who has access to both,
    your computer and the external media, can decrypt the password-file! Never
    leave the computer and the media unattended at the same place! Connect
    this media only while logon and don't use it if other persons have
    root-access to your computer.</para>

    <para>If you want to save your password, first connect the external media
    to your computer. The media must be mounted, you must have write access to
    it and it must be a removable device.</para>

    <para><graphic depth="11.643cm" fileref="pwsave.png"
    width="14.553cm" /></para>

    <para>Chose the path to the mounted device, invoke your password twice
    into the password fields and click “Save”. A hidden directory
    “<filename>.fingerprints</filename>“ will be created in the given path and
    a file “<filename>&lt;username&gt;@&lt;hostname&gt;.xml</filename>“ will
    be created there. This file contains the encrypted login password.
    Moreover a file
    „<filename>/var/lib/fingerprint-gui/&lt;username&gt;/config.xml</filename>“
    will be created on your local harddrive containing the UUID of the media,
    the given path and the key to decrypt the password.</para>

    <para><remark>Note:</remark> If you later change your login password, you
    need to repeat this process.</para>

    <para>You can now exit the program by clicking “Finish”.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Special Settings</title>

    <para>Here are some special settings for advanced users, that can not be
    automatically setup by the installation.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Disabling the User List</title>

      <para>In the menu "System | Administration | Login Screen" it is
      possible to disable the "Show list of users" item. While login there is
      shown only a text field for typing the username then. For showing the
      fingerprint request below this field the file
      "<filename>/etc/pam.d/gdm</filename>" must be changed. Insert the
      following text as the first line: <command>auth optional
      pam_fingerprint-gui.so -d</command></para>

      <para>Please check the file
      "<filename>/etc/pam.d/common-auth</filename>" for having the argument
      "<parameter>try_first_identified</parameter>" in the line with the
      <command>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</command> entry. If missing, append this
      argument to the line. You need root permissions to make changes to these
      files.</para>

      <para>If this is properly setup and the user list is disabled, you
      should be identified by your fingerprint and logged-in
      automatically.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Authentication by Policykit-1</title>

      <para>The autentication by policykit-1 is performed by the
      <command>polkit-gnome-authentication-agent</command>, that is started
      for each session. For starting this agent a starter file
      "<filename>/etc/xdg/autostart/polkit-gnome-authentication-agent.desktop</filename>"
      is used. By the installation of fingerprint-gui a starter
      "<filename>/etc/xdg/autostart/fingerprint-polkit-agent.desktop</filename>"
      has been added to this directory, that starts the
      <command>fingerprint-polkit-agent</command>. To avoid conflicts between
      these two agents, the file
      "<filename>polkit-gnome-authentication-agent.desktop</filename>" must be
      removed from "<filename>/etc/xdg/autostart</filename>". After removing
      you need to logoff and login again for being able to authenticate by
      fingerprint in policykit-1.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>NVM Emulation</title>

      <para>The installation package installs default settings for UKEK
      devices that require NVM emulation. However it might be necessary to
      fine tune these settings. Below are quoted some excerpts from the
      documentation for UPEK fingerprint scanners:</para>

      <para>1 Introduction</para>

      <para>UPEK TCD4C and TCD4E sensors exist in two variants - with and
      without the EEPROM chip. The NVM functionality for sensors without
      EEPROM must be emulated. BSAPI for Linux uses file emulation for NVM
      functionality. This document describes the fundamental
      configuration.</para>

      <para>...</para>

      <para>2 NVM emulation configuration</para>

      <para>NVM contents for EEPROMless sensors is stored in files. There is
      one file per sensor. The location of these files is determined by
      'nvmprefix' configuration parameter. This parameter contains a path to
      NVM-emulation files and a prefix of their names. This allows (for
      example) to make the files hidden (names start by '.'). The 'nvmprefix'
      parameter can be set the following way: …</para>

      <para>As root create the configuration file
      “<filename>/etc/upek.cfg</filename>“ with the following line
      (Example):</para>

      <para><command>nvmprefix="/var/upek_data/.NVM"</command></para>

      <para>...</para>

      <para>The setup directory must have read and write access rights set for
      everyone who can use BSAPI. The /etc/upek.cfg file must have read access
      right set for everybody.</para>

      <para>...</para>

      <para>3 Additional DSN parameters</para>

      <para>The EEPROMless sensors are preconfigured for dual direction
      swipes. If you prefer to swipe only in one direction, you can override
      this setting by using dualswipe=0 parameter. ...In the /etc/upek.cfg
      configuration file Add the following line to the file:</para>

      <para><command>dualswipe=0</command></para>

      <para>...</para>

      <para><remark>Note:</remark> Use the 'dualswipe' parameter only in the
      cofiguration where you have used the 'nvmprefix' parameter.</para>

      <para>…</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Installed Files and Helper Applications</title>

      <para>Fingerprint GUI makes use of the following programs, helper
      applications, libraries and files. Depending of  compiler settings while
      creating the installation packages the location in the file system can
      differ slightly (located in <filename>/usr/...</filename> or
      <filename>/usr/local/...</filename>).<orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/usr/local/bin/fingerprint-gui</filename></para>

            <para>Main application for enrollment and verification of
            fingerprints and for special settings;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/usr/local/bin/fingerprint-identifier</filename></para>

            <para>Program for testing fingerprint identification, usable in
            scripts and other applications. The login name of the  identified
            user is printed to stdout;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/usr/local/lib/fingerprint-gui/fingerprint-helper</filename></para>

            <para>Helper application for prompting finger swipes out of
            PAM;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/usr/local/lib/fingerprint-gui/fingerprint-plugin</filename></para>

            <para>Helper application for embedding the finger swipe dialog
            into the gnome-screensaver instead of a on screen keyboard;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/usr/local/lib/fingerprint-gui/fingerprint-rw</filename></para>

            <para>Helper application for reading and writing fingerprint data and settings with required
            permissions;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/usr/local/lib/fingerprint-gui/fingerprint-polkit-agent</filename></para>

            <para>Authentication agent for policykit-1;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/lib/security/pam_fingerprint-gui.so</filename></para>

            <para>PAM library module for identification and authentication of
            users by their fingerprints;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/var/lib/fingerprint-gui/&lt;benutzername&gt;</filename></para>

            <para>Directory per user to store fingerprints and user settings
            to.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Debugging</title>

      <para>All programs and libraries can create debug output in syslog (auth
      facility), if they are called with the argument
      “<parameter>-d</parameter>“ or “<parameter>--debug</parameter>“. By
      default the debug output goes to
      <filename>/var/log/auth.log</filename>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Special Arguments</title>

      <para>“<parameter>decorated</parameter>” - Argument given on the command
      line to <command>fingerprint-identifier</command> shows the finger swipe
      dialog as decorated window. Default is undecorated;</para>

      <para>“<parameter>try_first_identified</parameter>” - Argument given to
      <command>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</command> in PAM configuration files
      causes <command>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</command> to return “PAM_SUCCESS”
      immediately if the given user was identified already by a previous run
      of the module in the same PAM stack.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Online-Help</title>

      <para>Online-Help is available in the Fingerprint GUI forum on:</para>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://home.ullrich-online.cc/fingerprint/Forum">http://home.ullrich-online.cc/fingerprint/Forum</ulink></para>

      <para>or on the homepage:</para>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://www.ullrich-online.cc/fingerprint">http://www.ullrich-online.cc/fingerprint</ulink></para>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>
