<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Fingerprint GUI Step-by-Step Manual</title>

    <subtitle>Package Maintainer's Manual (version 1.07)</subtitle>

    <author>
      <firstname>Wolfgang</firstname>

      <surname>Ullrich</surname>
    </author>

    <date>2015-06-29</date>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>This guide is not intended for normal users. It is intended for
    package maintainers and those advanced users, who want to test Fingerprint
    GUI on a Linux system, that has no installation package available yet. All
    settings, filenames and locations, packet names and so on are based on a
    fresh installation of Ubuntu Linux 10.10. Ubuntu users, who want to use
    Fingerprint GUI only, can install a package from a personal package
    archive (ppa) on <ulink
    url="https://launchpad.net/~fingerprint/+archive/fingerprint-gui">https://launchpad.net/~fingerprint/+archive/fingerprint-gui</ulink>
    that is maintained by David Jurenka.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Debugging and Getting Help</title>

      <para>If you encounter any problems with your installation, please try
      to debug. When started with the “<parameter>-d</parameter>” (or
      “<parameter>--debug</parameter>”) argument, all executables print lots
      of debug output to the auth facility of syslog. The debug output goes by
      default into <filename>/var/log/auth.log</filename>. If this can't solve
      the problem, try to get help by using the forum on <ulink
      url="http://home.ullrich-online.cc/fingerprint/Forum/">http://home.ullrich-online.cc/fingerprint/Forum/</ulink>
      or looking at the homepage <ulink
      url="http://www.ullrich-online.cc/fingerprint/">http://www.ullrich-online.cc/fingerprint/</ulink>
      for newest informations and known bugs. If this doesn't help, contact me
      (the author) directly by mail to
      contact_at_ullrich_dash_online_dot_cc.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Distribution</title>

      <para>Since version 1.00 the software is not distributed as executable
      binaries any more on the homepage. If there is no installation package
      available for your system, you need to compile and install by makefile.
      Please read the README file for information about compiling and
      installing.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Library Dependencies</title>

      <para>On Ubuntu 10.10 the following libraries (incl. their development
      headers) must be installed: libfakekey, libqca2, libpam0g, libfprint,
      libusb-1.0-0, qt4-dev-tools, libpolkit-qt-1. Other Linux distributions
      might require more packages to be installed or might have different
      package names.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Conflicting Software</title>

      <para>The following applications are known to conflict with Fingerprint
      GUI: <command>thinkfinger</command>, <command>pam-fprint,
      pam-fprintd</command> and, of course, earlier versions of
      <command>Fingerprint GUI</command>. Remove these software and undo all
      configuration changes made for them.</para>

      <para><remark>IMPORTANT NOTE ABOUT KDE:</remark> Because
      <command>kdm</command> and <command>kscreenlocker</command> don't meet
      the requirements in the “<ulink
      url="http://www.kernel.org/pub/linux/libs/pam/Linux-PAM-html/adg-overview.html">PAM
      Application Developers Guide</ulink>” they will not work (see <ulink
      url="https://bugs.kde.org/show_bug.cgi?id=105631">Bug 105631</ulink>).
      Please don't report “bugs” against Fingerprint GUI about login or
      unlocking the screensaver on KDE systems. Other services like
      <command>su</command>, <command>sudo</command>,
      <command>kdesudo</command> and <command>policykit-1</command> should
      work. At least on Kubuntu 10.10 they do.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Installing Fingerprint GUI</title>

    <para>When installing by executing “<command>sudo make install</command>”
    the following files and directories are installed to your system:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/usr/local/bin/</filename>:
        <command>fingerprint-gui</command>,
        <command>fingerprint-identifier</command>;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/usr/local/lib/fingerprint-gui/</filename>:
        <command>fingerprint-helper</command>,
        <command>fingerprint-plugin</command>,
        <command>fingerprint-polkit-agent</command>,
        <command>fingerprint-rw</command> with symlinks <command>fingerprint-rw-write</command> and <command>fingerprint-rw-read</command>;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/lib/security/</filename>:
        <command>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</command>;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/var/lib/</filename>:
        <filename>fingerprint-gui/</filename> (directory for user fingerprint
        data);</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/usr/share/applications/</filename>:
        <filename>fingerprint-gui.desktop</filename>;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename>:
        <filename>fingerprint-gui/</filename> (directory containing html
        documentation);</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/usr/share/man/man.1/</filename>:
        <filename>fingerprint-gui.1.gz</filename>,
        <filename>fingerprint-identifier.1.gz</filename>,
        <filename>pam_fingerprint-gui.1.gz</filename>;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/etc/xdg/autostart/</filename>:
        <filename>fingerprint-polkit-agent.desktop</filename>;</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>When installing the proprietary driver
    “<filename>libbsapi.so</filename>” for fingerprint scanners manufactured
    by UPEK Inc. or SGS Thomson, that is made by executing “<command>sudo make
    install-upek</command>”, the following additional files and directories
    are installed:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/etc/</filename>:
        <filename>upek.cfg</filename>;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/var/</filename>: <filename>upek_data/</filename>
        (directory for NVM emulation);</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>in <filename>/etc/udev/rules.d/</filename>:
        <filename>91-fingerprint-gui-upek-rules</filename>;</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Accessing Fingerprint Devices</title>

    <para>For Fingerprint GUI to work, all users need read and write
    permissions to the connected fingerprint reader. By default you need a
    group named “plugdev” that all users are members of. If you don't want to
    create or use this group you need to change the group name in the udev
    rules file and restart or reconfigure udev with udevadm.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>First Start and Enrolling Fingerprints</title>

    <para>By default a start entry “Fingerprint GUI” is installed in the
    “System | Preferences” menu. Start Fingerprint GUI from there or start it
    in a terminal with “<command>fingerprint-gui -d</command>”. Enroll your
    fingerprints. The “Test” button in the “Settings” tab will
    <command>not</command> work in this stage yet. If acquiring fingerprints
    does work with Fingerprint GUI you can go ahead with the system
    configuration.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>System Configuration</title>

    <para>Because configuration errors can lock access to your system
    completely, you should always keep open a root session in a secure tty for
    being able to undo configuration changes.</para>

    <para>You need root permissions to make the following changes.</para>

    <para>The following settings are only examples, working on Ubuntu 10.10,
    that demonstrate the configuration principles. On other Linux
    distributions the filenames in question or file contents might
    differ.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Configuring the PAM Stack</title>

      <para>First of all make a copy of your <filename>/etc/pam.d/</filename>
      directory. So you can easily revert all changes if something goes
      wrong.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Edit the file <filename>/etc/pam.d/common-auth</filename>:
          insert a line “<command>auth sufficient pam_fingerprint-gui.so -d
          try_first_identified</command>” before the line “<command>auth …
          pam_unix.so ...</command>”, so that
          <command>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</command> is called before a
          password is requested;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Edit the file <filename>/etc/pam.d/gdm</filename>: insert a
          line “<command>auth optional pam_fingerprint-gui.so -d</command>”,
          so that <command>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</command> is called as a
          first action when a user performs a login;</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>These settings assume, that all other configuration files for the
      PAM authentication services include the file
      “<filename>common-auth</filename>”.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Configuring Gnome-Screensaver</title>

      <para><command>Gnome-screensaver</command> needs a plugin for showing a
      widget that requests a finger-swipe from the user when he tries to
      unlock the screensaver. This plugin is configured as an “embedded
      keyboard” in the <command>gnome-screensaver</command> settings. Open the
      “<command>gconf-editor</command>”, find the “apps | gnome-screensaver”
      entry and edit the “embedded_keyboard_command”. Edit the command line to
      “<filename>/usr/local/lib/fingerprint-gui/fingerprint-plugin
      -d</filename>” and enable the “embedded_keyboard_enabled”
      checkbox.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Configuring Policykit-1</title>

      <para>For authenticating by <command>policykit-1</command> a polkit
      authentication agent must run in every user's session. Therefore the
      file “<filename>fingerprint-polkit-agent.desktop</filename>” is
      installed to <filename>/etc/xdg/autostart/</filename> by “<command>sudo
      make install</command>”. This file starts the
      <command>fingerprint-polkit-agent</command> when a user session is
      started. But the <command>fingerprint-polkit-agent</command> conflicts
      with the “<command>polkit-gnome-authentication-agent-1</command>” or the
      “<command>polkit-kde-authentication-agent-1</command>” that are
      installed by default on your system. To solve this conflict remove the
      “<filename>polkit-gnome-authentication-agent-1.desktop</filename>” or
      “<filename>polkit-kde-authentication-agent-1.desktop</filename>” file
      from the directory <filename>/etc/xdg/autostart/</filename>.</para>

      <para>Brave users can restart their system now. The less brave should
      continue with some tests as follows:</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Testing the System</title>

    <para>The following should work after configuration is done:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><command>sudo</command>: Open a terminal and type “<command>sudo
        xterm</command>”. In the terminal should appear a line prompting for a
        password while at the same time a GUI widget should request a
        finger-swipe. You should be able to open <command>xterm</command> with
        root permissions by typing your password and by swiping your finger
        over the reader as well.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>su</command>: If you have registered a fingerprint for
        the root user (start <command>fingerprint-gui</command> with
        <command>sudo</command> to do this), you can “<command>su</command>”
        with root's finger. Open a terminal and type “<command>su</command>”.
        The terminal should prompt as follows:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <para>Password:</para>

          <para>Fingerprint Login 1.07</para>

          <para>Authenticating root</para>

          <para>Swipe your finger or type your password:</para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>No GUI widget should appear and you should be able to
        “<command>su</command>” with root's password or root's
        fingerprint.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>login</command> (in a secure tty): Change to a secure
        tty (<command>Ctrl-Alt_F2</command>), type your username and press
        enter. You'll be prompted with:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <para>Password:</para>

          <para>Fingerprint Login 1.07</para>

          <para>Authenticating &lt;username&gt;</para>

          <para>Swipe your finger or type your password:</para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>You should be able to login with your password or your
        fingerprint.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>gnome-screensaver</command>: Lock your screen and move
        the mouse. The unlock dialog should appear and a GUI widget requesting
        a finger-swipe should appear below. Unlocking should work with
        password and with fingerprint.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>gdm login</command>: Logout from your gnome session and
        try to login with your fingerprint again. Please note: This will not
        work if you have an encrypted home directory. Please read about
        “password on external media” in the user's manual about this problem
        and it's solution.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>policykit-1</command>: Before you can test
        <command>policykit-1</command> you must reboot or kill the
        “<command>polkit-gnome-authentication-agent-1</command>” or the
        “<command>polkit-kde-authentication-agent-1</command>” for your
        session and start the
        <command>/usr/lib/fingerprint-polkit-agent</command> manually. Then
        open “System | Administration | Users and Groups” and click the
        “Advanced Settings” button. A GUI dialog should appear, requesting a
        password and a finger-swipe for a user with administration rights.
        Unlocking the advanced settings should be possible with fingerprint
        and with password as well.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Advanced Tests</title>

    <para>By default, the <command>GDM</command> (and other display managers)
    login screen presents a list of users possible for login. Fingerprint GUI
    is not only able to authenticate a user by his fingerprint but can
    “identify” the user by a one-to-many comparison of the given finger-swipe
    to all available fingerprint data for login. This allows to “switch off”
    the userlist and to identify and login an user only by his fingerprint. On
    Ubuntu 10.10 you can open “System | Administration | Login Screen”, unlock
    it and uncheck the “Show list of users” entry. On other
    <command>GDM</command> versions you can execute the following command to
    disable the user list (this is one line): "<command>sudo gconftool-2
    --direct --config-source xml:readwrite:/etc/gconf/gconf.xml.defaults
    --type bool --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/disable_user_list
    true</command>". After this is done, you can logout. The GDM greeter
    should show only the username-prompt and the fingerprint widget now. By
    swiping your finger, the system should recognize you and login you
    immediately.</para>

    <para>When authenticating an user for an administrative task by
    <command>policykit-1</command>, an user who is member of the admin group
    is requested to authenticate. If there are more than one users members of
    this group, a list of admin users is shown by
    <command>fingerprint-polkit-agent</command> for selecting the user to be
    authenticated. You should be able to select the user and, depending
    whether fingerprint data for this user is availbale, the fingerprint
    widget should be shown or not below the password field for authentication.
    If the current user is member of the admin group, this user will be
    preselected.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Known Limitations</title>

    <para>While requesting a finger-swipe, the fingerprint device is opened
    exclusively. This means you can not authenticate by fingerprint for more
    than one service at the same time. For example you can not request
    “<command>su</command>” in one terminal and “<command>sudo</command>
    something” in another. In this case both authentications will fail.</para>

    <para>Because <command>pam_fingerprint-gui.so</command> always requests a
    fingerprint and a password at the same time, an &lt;enter&gt; key is fed
    into the password prompt by <command>libfakekey</command> or
    <command>uinput</command>, when the user was authenticated by his
    fingerprint. If the keyboard focus has been moved away from the requesting
    application, this &lt;enter&gt; key can not complete the password prompt
    and the authentication procedure “hangs”. For example open two terminals,
    then perform a “<command>sudo</command> something” in one terminal and
    click into the other one before swiping your finger. The authentication
    for <command>sudo</command> will fail.</para>
  </sect1>
</article>
